District Court of Potsdam
10 December 1955
Verdict in trial for quadruple murder
Defendant: Wilhelm Antonius Wehren,
born on 30 May 1918 in Essen.
Place of crime: Herzsprung, near Wittstock (on the Dosse).
Date of crime: 30 April 1945.
Victims: Prisoners of Polish nationality,
identity unknown.
Willi Wehren is 21 when the war begins.
In the summer of 1939,
he is drafted into the Wehrmacht.
Wehren soon attracts negative attention:
accused of slander and the receipt of stolen goods,
he is tried by a military tribunal.
In 1943, he is ultimately accused of undermining military morale.
Wehren is sent to Sachsenhausen Concentration Camp.
It seems his fate is sealed.
But in April 1945, his fortunes turn.
The war’s end is looming.
The concentration camp is to be evacuated.
To do so, the SS also enlists inmates as guards.
Willi Wehren is recruited as well,
and is put in uniform again.
Issued with a rifle and ammunition,
he’s assigned to a column of five hundred women.
On 22 April, they set off on the long journey to the north.
Theirs is the last group to march from Sachsenhausen.
They wear little more than their threadbare prisoners’ uniforms.
Not all of them have shoes.
Many walk in wooden clogs or improvise with rags wrapped around their feet.
They walk day after day. Sometimes it’s 40 km, sometimes 20.
The thermometer barely gets gets above 0°C.
They sometimes find a barn for the night.
But more often, they sleep out in the open.
Meanwhile, Wehren continues his rise.
He receives a motorcycle.
As a despatch rider,
he maintains contact between marching groups.
He also has to look after the provisioning of his assigned group.
The march is torturous.
The prisoners are weakened by their long internment.
Many are sick and starved.
Those who can’t keep up are shot by the SS
and kicked into the ditch.
More than a thousand dead are left on the roads and fields.
Whoever can, keeps going.
Endless processions of misery traverse the roads and villages.
There’s well over thirty thousand people.
Everyone can see them.
Hardly anyone feels sympathy for the prisoners,
and very few have the courage to help them.
Most react with mistrust, fear, or indifference.
So too in the little village of Herzsprung.
It’s here in this village that Willi Wehren has abandoned his unit.
He meets a man named Berger.
This is another ex-prisoner who was hastily put in uniform
when the death march began.
Wehren has taken up residence at the local inn.
He knows the innkeeper from before:
Wilhelm Leppin is an important man in Herzsprung.
He owns the inn and is also the local Nazi Party chief.
In this village, he’s in charge
... and the locals follow him willingly.
It’s Monday, the 30th of April.
In the morning, a 10-year-old boy comes running up to Leppin:
his mother has found four runaway prisoners in the barn!
Leppin, Wehren, and Berger
immediately rush to the woman’s farm
and find four frightened Polish prisoners
who had managed to escape the death march.
They force them out of hiding.
Wehren starts beating them.
Leppin finds a cudgel.
He likewise beats them and yells:
‘Come out here, you swine!’
The three men talk it over.
They don’t want any hassle.
To them, the Poles are a burden.
Leppin decides it’d be best to get rid of them.
A family in Herzsprung is getting ready to flee
from the approaching Red Army.
They suddenly hear a clamour outside their window.
The Polish prisoners are being herded through Herzsprung,
across the village road and past the local homes to the village outskirts.
The family watches the entourage with its trail of curious onlookers,
including several children.
Just before the gravel pit, on a small tree-covered slope,
the procession comes to a halt.
Among them is the local Nazi official Leppin.
He stays somewhat apart, smoking a cigar,
but follows the proceedings closely.
A scuffle begins.
One of the prisoners tries to escape.
Willi Wehren chases him and shoots.
The victim goes down, but is still alive.
Wehren flips him over with his foot and kills him
him with a shot to the back of the neck.
Berger and Wehren now force the remaining prisoners
around the slope to Herzsprung’s gravel pit.
What happens next is not visible to the onlookers.
But the tommy gun’s shots still echo through the whole village.
[shoots firing]
The villagers watch transfixed.
Seven witnesses claim they saw or heard
for themselves the execution of the camp prisoners.
They testify that other villagers
also followed the events from close up.
On 10 December 1955,
the Potsdam District Court sentences Wilhelm Wehren
to death for quadruple murder.
A year later, his sentence is commuted to life imprisonment.
In August 1975,
Wehren is pardoned and released from prison.
He moves to West Germany.
Leppin is arrested by the Soviet military authorities in May 1945.
As a Nazi Party official,
he is sent to an internment camp.
He is released in August 1948.
He is never charged for the murders in Herzsprung.
The case against Leppin is dismissed due to his ‘minor responsibility’.
He remains unpunished.
A denunciation, a capture, a public execution.
In broad daylight, in the middle of the village, in view of the people.
They stick together, and beyond the mass murder too:
the bodies are quickly buried, and with them,
the knowledge of that heinous event.
In Herzsprung, a silence gradually settles.
Soon, there is no one here who still remembers the Polish prisoners
that were executed in the village.
Their names remain unknown.
Animation: Cosimo Miorelli
Written and directed by: Nina Mair, Matthias Neumann
Music: Morgan Hickinbotham
Narrator: Nina West
Sound design: Felicitas Heck
Video editors: Nina Mair, Riccardo Bernardi
Supervisors (Stiftung BG): David Rojkowski, Carmen Lange, Maren Jung-Diestelmeier
Consultant: Martin Clemens Winter