There wasn’t any resistance.
We didn’t have to force our way in.
We simply drove in.
There was just this big gate.
And we opened it.
The first thing I saw were the barracks, but no people.
They were hiding.
They still didn’t know the war was over.
I didn't really understand that we were liberated.
Not until the war was over.
I didn’t have any sense of real happiness.
I felt alone,
in every way.
Maybe it would’ve been different
if my parents had still been with me.
Thomas Bürgenthal is a child,
just 10 years old.
He arrives at Sachsenhausen
having already come a long way.
For four long years,
he and his family are stuck  in the Kielce Ghetto.
In 1944, he is deported to Auschwitz-Birkenau
and separated from his parents.
In January 1945,
Auschwitz is evacuated.
Joining the children’s section of the death march,
Thomas walks for days through ice and snow.
A train finally brings them to Oranienburg.
His feet are half-frozen as he enters the camp,
just outside town.
During these days,
many transports arrive at Sachsenhausen.
The camp is hopelessly overcrowded.
Up to a hundred inmates die every day.
Thomas Bürgenthal is in a great deal of pain.
The toes of his right foot are getting darker and darker.
He is sent to the infirmary.
He’s afraid of this facility,
because at Auschwitz it was the most certain way to the gas chamber.
He’s told to remove his shoes.
A doctor examines his feet.
The boy is laid on a wooden table.
Two men come over and grab his arms and legs.
They hold him down.
Thomas starts screaming.
They put a white cloth over his face
and he quickly loses consciousness.
When he wakes up,
he’s in a sickroom.
Two toes from his right foot have been amputated.
Bernhard Storch swears to give his life
for Poland in the battle against the German army.
He swears absolute loyalty to the Soviet Union
in the fight against their common enemy.
Bernhard Storch is 16 when the Germans invade Poland.
He’s Jewish.
He escapes the looming persecution and goes to the Soviet Union.
There, in the spring of 1943,
he joins a Polish unit of the Red Army.
He believes this to be his only way back home.
Their division includes more than twelve thousand men.
Storch joins the artillery.
He enters the war with the Belorussian Front.
As they advance,
they follow a trail of devastation and horror.
In a forest, they discover a railway track
which leads them to a place called Sobibor.
But there’s nothing there.
Only bare soil with a few trees,
and not a single soul.
There’s no one around
who could tell them what happened here.
They have no time to stop somewhere,
no time to think.
The war’s imperatives push them onwards.
They reach Majdanek.
This place of horror has also been abandoned.
They find thousands of suitcases and mountains of shoes,
and Storch fears that the personal effects might include those of his family,
whose whereabouts are unknown to him.
They move on.
Storch looks down at himself.
He sees his shoes.
They’re all white.
White from the crematorium ashes
that are scattered over the surrounding fields.
In April 1945,
Storch’s division reaches the Oder river.
He sees how the river is filled with soldiers’ blood, and bodies,
but must keep advancing without looking back.
At the same time,
things are getting worse around Oranienburg too.
In March and April 1945,
the town is heavily bombarded by air.
The front line is getting closer.
With the Battle of the Seelow Heights,
the Red Army begins its final push: The Berlin Offensive.
Nearby at Sachsenhausen Concentration Camp,
Thomas Bürgenthal hears the Allied bombers.
Lying in the infirmary barracks,
he dreams himself away.
He imagines one of the big planes coming down and lifting
the barracks with a big hook, taking it away to England or America.
One morning,
the sun is shining through the infirmary’s small window.
Thomas Bürgenthal wakes up.
He limps out onto the muster ground.
It’s completely empty!
The SS has evacuated the camp.
He looks up at the balcony of the administration building.
There’s no longer anyone behind the big machine gun.
The other watchtowers too: abandoned.
Suddenly he hears a creaking sound.
The big gate is opening.
He sees some soldiers getting out of a military vehicle.
They don’t look like SS.
They’ve got uniforms he’s never seen before.
And then the camp’s bell starts ringing.
One of the soldiers is striking it with all his strength
while another shouts across the muster ground:
‘Hitler kaput! Hitler kaput!’
When Bernhard Storch enters the camp,
he doesn’t see the inmates right away.
They stay in their barracks and hide.
But then they’re there.
It’s the first time
that they’re liberating people.
There are thousands of them, including many women,
with wretched clothes and shorn hair.
They’re hardly recognizable as human beings.
They weep unceasingly.
The liberators distribute water among the prisoners
and assure them that their troubles are over.
They are free.
Thomas Bürgenthal roams the camp
and discovers an unlocked office.
A portrait of Hitler hangs above the desk.
He climbs up and tears down the picture.
He dashes it on the floor.
The frame breaks and the glass shatters.
He spits on it and tramples Hitler’s face with such rage that his feet hurt,
but he keeps going until the picture is in tatters.
Thomas Bürgenthal leaves Oranienburg with the Polish Kościuszko Division.
It’s in Berlin that he sees the end of the war.
They take him to a Jewish orphanage near Warsaw.
Bürgenthal’s father is murdered at the camp in Flossenbürg.
His mother Gerda survives, and after several months, she finds her son in Poland.
They move to Göttingen. In 1951, Bürgenthal emigrates to the USA.
After the fall of Berlin,
Bernhard Storch returns to Poland in search of his family.
They’re all dead.Their home is destroyed.
He never returns to his home town again.
In September 1945, he marries his wife Ruth in Katowice.
In April 1947, with two suitcases and $20, they board a ship for New York.
Animation:
Cosimo Miorelli
Written and directed by:
Nina Mair & Matthias Neumann
Music:
Morgan Hickinbotham
Narrator:
Nina West
Sound design:
Felicitas Heck
Video editors:
Nina Mair, Riccardo Bernardi
Supervisors:
Mareike Otters, Maren Jung-Diestelmeier