District Court of Potsdam. 10 December 1955.
Verdict in trial for quadruple murder.
Defendant: Wilhelm Antonius Wehren,
born in Essen on 30 May 1918.
Place of crime: Herzsprung,
near Wittstock (on the Dosse).
Date of crime: 30 April 1945.
Victims: Prisoners of Polish nationality,
identity unknown.
Willi Wehren is 21 when the war begins.
In the summer of 1939, he is drafted
into the Wehrmacht.
Wehren soon attracts negative attention:
accused of slander,
he is tried by a military tribunal.
In 1943, he is ultimately accused
of undermining military morale.
Wehren is sent to
Sachsenhausen Concentration Camp.
It seems his fate is sealed.
But in April 1945, his fortunes turn.
The war’s end is looming.
The concentration camp is to be evacuated.
To do so, the SS also enlists inmates as guards.
Willi Wehren is recruited as well,
and is put in uniform again.
Issued with a rifle and ammunition,
he’s assigned to a column of five hundred women.
On 22 April, they set off
on the long journey to the north.
Theirs is the last group to march
from Sachsenhausen.
They wear little more than their threadbare
prisoners’ uniforms. Not all of them have shoes.
Many walk in wooden clogs
or improvise with rags wrapped around their feet.
They walk day after day.
Sometimes it’s 40 km, sometimes 20.
The thermometer barely gets above 0°C.
They sometimes find a barn for the night.
But more often, they sleep out in the open.
Meanwhile, Wehren continues his rise.
He receives a motorcycle.
As a despatch rider, he maintains contact
between marching groups.
He also has to look after the provisioning
of his group.
The march is torturous.
The prisoners are weakened
by their long internment.
Many are sick and starved.
Those who can’t keep up are shot by the SS
and kicked into the ditch.
More than a thousand dead are left
on the roads and fields.
Whoever can, keeps going.
Endless processions of misery
traverse the roads and villages.
There’s well over thirty thousand people.
Everyone can see them.
Hardly anyone feels sympathy for the prisoners,
and very few have the courage to help them.
Most react with mistrust, fear, or indifference.
So too in the little village of Herzsprung.
It’s here in this village
that Willi Wehren has abandoned his unit.
He meets a man named Berger.
This is another ex-prisoner who was hastily put
in uniform when the death march began.
Wehren has taken up residence at the local inn.
He knows the innkeeper from before:
Wilhelm Leppin is an important man in Herzsprung.
He owns the inn
and is also the local Nazi Party chief.
In this village, he’s in charge...
...and the locals follow him willingly.
It’s Monday, the 30th of April.
In the morning, a 10-year-old boy comes
running up to Leppin with urgent news:
his mother has found four runaway prisoners
in the barn!
Leppin, Wehren, and Berger immediately rush
to the woman’s farm
and find four frightened Polish prisoners
who had managed to escape the death march.
They force them out of hiding.
Wehren starts beating them.
Leppin finds a cudgel.
He likewise beats them and yells:
‘Come out here, you swine!’
The three men talk it over.
They don’t want any hassle.
To them, the Poles are a burden.
Leppin decides it’d be best to get rid of them.
A family in Herzsprung is getting ready to flee
from the approaching Red Army.
They suddenly hear a clamour
outside their window.
The Polish prisoners are being herded
through Herzsprung,
across the village road and past the local homes
to the village outskirts.
The family watches the entourage with its trail of
curious onlookers, including several children.
Just before the gravel pit, on a small tree-covered slope,
the procession comes to a halt.
Among them is the local Nazi official Leppin.
He stays somewhat apart, smoking a cigar,
but follows the proceedings closely.
A scuffle begins.
One of the prisoners tries to escape.
Willi Wehren chases him and shoots.
The victim goes down, but is still alive.
Wehren flips him over with his foot
and kills him with a second shot.
Berger and Wehren now force the remaining prisoners
around the slope to the gravel pit.
What happens next is not visible to the onlookers.
But the tommy gun’s shots still echo
through the whole village.
The villagers watch transfixed.
Seven witnesses claim they saw or heard for themselves
the execution of the camp prisoners.
They testify that other villagers also followed
the events from close up.
On 10 Dec. 1955, the Potsdam District Court
sentences Wehren to death for quadruple murder.
A year later, his sentence is commuted
to life imprisonment.
In August 1975, Wehren is pardoned
and released from prison.
He moves to West Germany.
Leppin is arrested by the Soviet military authorities
in May 1945.
As a Nazi Party official,
he is sent to an internment camp.
He is released in August 1948.
He is never charged for the murders
in Herzsprung.
The case against Leppin is dismissed due to
his ‘minor responsibility’. He remains unpunished.
A denunciation, a capture, a public execution.
In broad daylight, in the middle of the village,
in view of the people.
They stick together, and beyond
the mass murder too:
the bodies are quickly buried, and with them,
the knowledge of that heinous event.
In Herzsprung, a silence gradually settles.
Soon, there is no one here who still remembers
the executed Polish prisoners.
Their names remain unknown.
Animation:
Cosimo Miorelli
Written and directed by:
Nina Mair & Matthias Neumann
Music:
Morgan Hickinbotham
Narrator:
Nina West
Sound design:
Felicitas Heck
Video editors:
Nina Mair, Riccardo Bernardi
Supervisors (Stiftung BG): David Rojkowski,
Carmen Lange, Maren Jung-Diestelmeier
Consultant: Martin Clemens Winter